Finding aid for Patricia Hill Burnett papers, 1967-2002
Bentley Historical Library
Patricia Hill Burnett papers
1967-2002
1967-1987
Bentley Historical Library
Burnett, Patricia Hill, 1920-
85105 Aa 2
12.5 linear feet
1 oversize boxes
1 oversize folder
Detroit portrait painter and feminist activist. Correspondence, printed material, newspaper clippings, photographs, reports, speeches, articles and other papers documenting her career as an artist, and with the Michigan Women's Commission, the National Association of Commissions for Women, the National Organization for Women (NOW) and other civic, Republican, and feminist organizations.
The papers were received from Patricia Hill Burnett (donor no. 5716 ) in various accessions beginning in 1975. Additional materials donated by Terrill H. Burnett (donor no. 11377 ) and Hillary Burnett (donor no. 11378 ), in November 2015.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research; photocopying of Burnett speeches in full is prohibited.
Patricia Hill Burnett (1920-2014), noted artist, feminist, and political activist, earned a four-year scholarship to the Toledo Museum of Art at the age of 12. She pursued her artistic studies at Goucher College, Wayne State University, the Instituto d'Allende, Mexico, and by private study with various artists. Throughout her life she was active as an artist. As Miss Michigan she was runner-up in the Miss America contest. She married William Anding Lange in 1945, whom she later divorced. They had one child. She later married Harry A. Burnett, with whom she had three more children.
In 1962 Patricia Hill Burnett broke the all-male barrier at the Detroit Scarab Club for artists. In 1969, Burnett organized the Michigan National Organization for Women (NOW), served as its president, 1969-1971, and convened NOW chapters throughout the state.
Her involvement with Michigan NOW led to a position on the NOW National Board, 1971-1975, and to the chair of NOW's International Committee. An inveterate traveler with a world view, Burnett was instrumental in expanding NOW into an international organization. She played a great part in organizing the International Feminist Planning Conference held at Harvard (May 1973) and convened the NOW International Feminist Conference in 1973. She also took an around-the-world trip the same year to survey the status of women in several countries. Through her organizational efforts, twenty-five NOW international affiliations were organized in twenty-one countries. Burnett was a NOW delegate to the United Nations' International Women's Year (IWY) conference in Mexico City in 1975, and to the IWY Houston Conference in 1977. As chair of the World Feminist Commission she hoped to organize the International Feminist Convention in Brussels in 1977. Burnett later attended the UN Decade for Women Copenhagen Conference in 1980. In 1987 Burnett traveled as a delegate of the International Women's Forum to honor President Corazon Aquino as Woman of the Year.
Burnett was instrumental in organizing the Michigan Women's Republican Caucus, which she has called the "first feminist Republican Women's Organization." Her other Republican Party activities have included the Michigan Issues Committee and the State Central Committee. Governor Milliken appointed her to the Michigan Women's Commission in 1973; she served first as vice-chair (1975) and then as chair (1976). After serving for four years on the executive board of directors of the National Association of Commissions for Women (NACW), Burnett was elected president of NACW in 1979.
Burnett was active in civic affairs, serving on the New Detroit Employment and Art Committees and the Detroit Human Rights Commission. She has also served as president of the Detroit House of Corrections, 1973-1976.
Patricia Hill Burnett has lectured on women in art, women in business, and, most widely, on feminism. As a portrait painter she inaugurated and executed a series of portraits of leading feminists. These were later placed in the "Women's Hall of Fame."
Due to her long career as a portrait painter, Burnett was called on to be one of twelve founding members of the Council of Leading American Painters which was responsible for the organization and promotion of the Nattional Portrait Seminar.
She received many honors for her artistic, business, and feminist activities. In 1987 Burnett was inducted into the Michigan Women's Hall of Fame, and in 1995 she published a memoir entitled True Colors: An Artist's Journey from Beauty Queen to Feminist.
Patricia Hill Burnett died in December 2014, at the age of 94.
The papers of Patricia Hill Burnett are organized into nine series: Biographical; Correspondence; Speeches, Publications, and Interviews; Topical Files; Talks; Trips; Hearings and Reports, Domestic Assault; Notebooks; and Art.
While most of the material relates directly to Patricia Hill Burnett, the papers also relate to the more general women's movement during the 1970s and early 1980s.
Art.; Artists.; Equal Rights Amendments -- United States.; Feminism.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1971-1980.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1974-1977.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1977-1981.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1969-1974.; Women's rights -- Michigan.; Women painters -- Michigan.; Painters -- Michigan.; Women in politics -- Michigan.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Activists.; Celebrities.; Feminists.; International Women's Year, 1975.; People associated with politics & government.; Women.; Copy prints.; Photographs.; Portraits.; Sound recordings.; Burnett, Patricia Hill, 1920-; Michigan. Women's Commission.; National Association of Commissions for Women.; National Organization for Women.; Republican Party (Mich.); Burnett, Patricia Hill, 1920-; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; National Women's Conference (1st: 1977: Houston, Tex.); World Conference of the International Women's Year (1975: Conference Centre of the Mexican Ministry of Foreign Affairs)
- Biographical
  The Biography series consists of clippings, resumes, printed awards, and printed brochures documenting Burnett's artistic career, her speaking career, and her work with NOW and other organizations.
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Clippings: Biographical, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Clippings, articles, resumes (Box 6)
  - Articles on art talks (Box 6)
  - Articles, original (Box 6)
  - Brochure (Box 6)
  - Awards, programs (Box 7)
  - Articles (Box 10)
- Correspondence, 1967-2002
  The Correspondence sereis, 1967-2002, consists of chronologically arranged material. Because the 1990 and 2015 accession material were not interfiled in with the earlier accession materials there are sometimes overlapping periods; where this has occurred the 1990 and 2015 accession materials have been designated as such. This series mainly documents Burnett's tenure as president of the National Association of Commissions for Women, and the National Organization for Women's International Feminist Conference (1973), which Burnett convened. Also documented is the controversy at NOW's National Board level concerning ballot voting, which resulted in a split in the National Board and nearly led to the destruction of NOW as a national organization.
  - 1967-1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1974 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1974 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1975 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1975 (Box 1)
  - 1975 (Box 1)
    (various)
  - January-June 1976 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1976 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1977 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1977 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1978 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1978 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1979 (Box 2)
  - July-September 1979 (Box 2)
  - October-December 1979 (Box 2)
  - 1970s (Box 2)
  - January-March 1980 (Box 2)
  - April-June 1980 (Box 2)
  - July-December 1980 (Box 2)
  - 1981 (Box 2)
  - 1982 (Box 2)
  - 1983 (Box 2)
  - 1984 (Box 2)
  - 1985, undated (Box 2)
  - 1976-1978 (Box 7)
  - 1966-2002, undated (Box 7)
  - Art correspondence, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - FBI (Box 7)
  - 1974-1992 (Box 7)
- Speeches, Publications, and Interviews
  Speeches, Publications, and Interviews, the third series, consists of speeches and articles written by Burnett throughout her career, as well as notes she gathered on the speeches. This series illustrates Burnett's attitudes on the role of women in American and international organizations, as well as the role of women in the artistic realm. Often, the sources Burnett used for her speeches and articles are reflected in both the Correspondence and Topical Files.
  - 1973-1987, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Articles (Box 2)
  - Book on Status of Women--Research Materials (Box 2)
  - General (Box 7)
  - Books (Box 7)
  - Speakers Bureau Information (Box 2)
  - Talks, 8 folders
  - General (Box 8)
  - Materials for Talks (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous/Miscellaneous Non-art talks, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Talks '84 (Box 8)
  - Women (Box 8)
  - "Art of the Portrait" Conference Talk (Box 9)
  - Art Talks (Box 9)
  - Dialogue on the Delights of Painting for the Amateur (Box 9)
  - Do Men and Women Speak the Same Language, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Glamor of an Art Career (Box 9)
  - Have Women Painters/Artists Been Brushed Aside, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Having It All and Loving It, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Introductions (Box 9)
  - Life in an Artists Studio (Box 9)
  - Life Lines (Box 9)
  - Michigan Women's Foundation (Box 9)
  - Painting the Famous and the Infamous, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Posing Your Sitter (Box 9)
  - Profiles of the Famous (Box 9)
  - Story of My Life, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Talk on "True Colors" (Box 9)
  - Talks (Box 9)
  - "Women Artists" Winning in the Portrait World" (Box 9)
  - Battered women (Box 10)
  - Cutups of Various Articles That May be Useful in the Future (Box 10)
  - Domestic Assault (Box 10)
  - Encounters with U.S. Presidents (Box 10)
  - Feminist Speeches (Box 10)
  - Health (Box 10)
  - How to Become a Woman Executive Up the Corporate Ladder, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - International (Box 10)
  - Ms Missing from "Old Masters" (Box 10)
  - My Working Palette (Box 10)
  - Now Was My Time (Box 10)
  - Oral History (Box 10)
  - Organizing an International Feminist Network (Box 10)
  - Reference for Future Talks (Box 10)
  - Research on Talks, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Sexual Harassment (Box 10)
  - Talk to Republican Convention, September 1988 (Box 10)
  - Testimony for the Hearing on the Republican Platform (Box 10)
  - The Progress of Women (Box 10)
  - Using the Right Side of the Brain in Portrait Painting (Box 10)
  - Will Women's Rights Go Wrong? (Box 10)
  - The Winds of Change are Blowing (Box 10)
  - Women on the Rise (Box 10)
  - Women Today in Russia, Israel, India & Thailand (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous/Collected (Box 13)
- Topical Files
  Topical Files consists of printed materials, notes, and some correspondence on issues and organizations from 1973 to 1980, as well as materials indicating her continued interest well into the mid-1990s and early 2000s. The material is arranged alphabetically by topic. Where topics are further divided, the material is arranged chronologically or alphabetically, as appropriate, under the indicated topical heading. This series should be used with the Correspondence series, as there is a great deal of overlap in topics covered as well as a great deal of correspondence concerning those topics.
  Burnett's work with the International Committee of NOW is represented very well in the Topical Files. This includes her work to organize the International Feminist Planning Conference (June 1973). There are two folders of general correspondence, mostly from women and/or women's groups in both Western and Eastern Europe, which, aside from describing who came to the planning conference, also gives a great deal of information on the status of feminist groups and ideologies during the mid-1970s. NOW materials also include a phonograph record with sound recordings titled "Equal Rights for Women Campaign."
  Information concerning the women's movement and feminism can also be found within the series on NOW International Actions in the section on the formation of international NOW chapters. Aside from documenting the formation of these international chapters these letters again reflect the status and ideologies of feminist groups and the women who founded them. There is also a great deal of peripheral information about the women's movement in general, including a small collection of pamphlets centered on providing aid to battered women, printed in Michigan.
  - Detroit House of Corrections (Box 2)
  - Detroit Human Rights Commission and Miscellaneous Activities, 1975-1978 (Box 2)
  - International Women's Year (IWY)
    - Houston Conference, 1977
      - General, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Printed material (Box 2)
      - Clippings (Box 2)
      - Photographs (Box 13)
    - Mexico City (Box 2)
    - Michigan (Box 2)
  - Michigan Women's Commission, 1976-1979; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Women's Organizations, Conferences, Issues
    - Printed material, 1976-1978 (Box 3)
    - Clippings, 1976-1978 (Box 3)
  - National Association of Commissions for Women (NACW), 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Northwood Institute (Box 3)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW)
    - Detroit NOW
      - General, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Board of Director meeting minutes, 1972 (Box 3)
    - International Committee
      - 1970-1972 (Box 3)
      - 1973 (Box 3)
      - 1974 (Box 3)
      - 1975 (Box 3)
      - Meeting minutes, 1974 (Box 3)
      - Undated (Box 3)
      - International Actions (Resolutions, petitions, and general materials relating to NOW chapters abroad.)
        - Political prisoners (Box 3)
        - International Chapters, Formation of
          - General materials (Box 3)
          - Africa (Box 3)
          - Australia (Box 3)
          - Bangladesh (Box 3)
          - Belgium (Box 3)
          - Brazil (Box 3)
          - Canada (Box 3)
          - Cuba (Box 3)
          - Denmark (Box 3)
          - England (UK, except Ireland) (Box 3)
          - Finland (Box 3)
          - France (Box 3)
          - Germany (Box 3)
          - Ghana (Box 3)
          - Guam (Box 3)
          - India (Box 3)
          - Iran (Box 3)
          - Ireland (Box 3)
          - Israel (Box 3)
          - Italy (Box 3)
          - Japan (Box 3)
          - Korea (Box 3)
          - Luxembourg (Box 3)
          - Marshall Islands (Box 3)
          - Mexico (Box 3)
          - Military (Box 3)
      - International Actions
        - International Chapters, Formation of
          - Netherlands (Box 3)
          - New Zealand (Box 3)
          - Nicaragua (Box 3)
          - Pakistan (Box 3)
          - Panama Canal Zone (Box 3)
          - Philippines (Box 3)
          - Puerto Rico (Box 3)
          - Sweden (Box 3)
          - Switzerland (Box 3)
          - Taiwan (Box 3)
          - Thailand (Box 3)
          - U.S.A. (includes Military APO), 3 folders (Box 3)
      - International Feminist Planning Conference, June 1973
        - General conference materials, 3 folders (Box 13)
        - General correspondence, 6 folders (Box 3)
        - Notes (Box 4)
        - Papers and Reports, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Michigan NOW (Box 4)
    - National NOW, 1966-1979
      - 1966-1972 (Box 4)
      - 1970 (Box 4)
      - 1971 (Box 4)
      - 1972 (Box 4)
      - 1973 (Box 4)
      - 1973 (Box 4)
      - 1974 (Box 4)
      - 1975 (Box 4)
      - 1975 (Box 4)
      - 1976 (Box 4)
      - 1976-1979 (Box 4)
      - Undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Clippings, 1973; undated (Box 4)
      - Printed Materials--NOW, other U.S. women's organizations, and ERA, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Executive Committee meeting minutes, 1971-1972 (scattered) (Box 4)
      - NOW and the law (Box 4)
      - Womansurge (Box 4)
      - World Feminist Commission, 1973-1978 (Box 4)
      - NOW Printed, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Newsletter (Do It NOW) (Box 4)
      - Equal Rights for Women Campaign (sound recording), 1 phonograph record
  - Republican Party, Michigan Women's Republican Caucus, 1973-1979 (Box 5)
  - UN Decade for Women, Copenhagen, July 1980 (Box 5)
  - U.S. National Women's Agenda, Task Force Plans of Action, Summary of Drafts, Washington, D.C., October 1-2, 1976 (Box 5)
  - White House Conference on Families, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - White House and Women (Box 5)
  - Women in Prison, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Women's Educational Equity Act (WEEA) (Box 5)
  - Women's Forum of Michigan (Box 5)
  - Women's International Network (WIN) (Box 5)
  - Zonta Club, 1975-1984 (Box 5)
  - Printed Materials -- NOW, other U.S. women's Organizations, and ERA (Box 8)
  - Victim Assault Pamphlets (Box 8)
  - Veteran Feminists of America, 1992-2002 (Box 9)
  - World Feminist Commission, 1982-2000 (Box 9)
  - Detroit NOW (Box 10)
  - NOW (Box 10)
  - Recollections of NOWZonta Club, 1994-1998 (Box 10)
- Talks
  - Child care (Box 5)
  - Creativity (notes) (Box 5)
  - International Planning Conference (Box 5)
  - Non-Nuclear Family (Box 5)
  - Non-Nuclear Family (Box 10)
  - NOW, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Women and Credit (Testimony for Michigan Women's Commission) (Box 5)
- Trips
  Thre Trips series is composed of materials that document Burnett's travels to France (1974), the Philippines (1987), and her around-the-world trip (1973) which includes her trip to the U.S.S.R.
  - Russia, October 1-15, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Around-the-World Trip, October 1-December 10, 1973 (Box 5)
  - French Trip, September 25-October 17, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Philippines Trip, August 5-7, 1987 (Box 5)
- Hearings and Reports, Domestic Assault
  The series Hearings And Reports, Domestic Assault consists of six volumes of hearings held in 1976 on domestic assault. The hearings were sponsored by the Michigan Women's Commission (MWC) and chaired by Burnett. The MWC reports on domestic assault were issued in 1977.
  - Notes and general correspondence, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Hearings: "The Physical Abuse of Women," Michigan Women's Commission, 1976; 6 volumes (Box 5)
  - Report: "Domestic Assault, a Report on Family Violence in Michigan," Michigan Women's Commission, 1977 (Box 5)
- Notebooks
  The series entitled Notebooks, consists of several notebooks. They document three International Feminist Conferences, especially the 1973 conference convened by Burnett; her organizational work with Michigan NOW; and her work with the NOW International Committee and NOW's affiliation with the UN.
  - "First Notebook" (Box 6)
  - December 1969-June 1974 (Box 6)
    (Notes on founding of Michigan NOW)
  - 1970, 1971 (Box 6)
  - International Feminist Conference (?), 1972; 2 volumes (Box 6)
  - 1972 New York and London and 1973 International Feminist Conference notes, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
  - International Feminist Conference notes, 1973 (Box 6)
  - United Nations, 1974 (Box 6)
  - 1974-1975, 1976; 1988; undated (Box 6)
  - Notes for book? (Box 6)
  - 1977 (Box 13)
- Art
  The final series, Art, further documents Butnett's artistic endeavors. The series consists of information about her involvement with the Portrait Club of New York, a collection of reference photographs of her portrait clients, a varied selection of photo duplications depicting Burnett's original pieces, and an original drawing and poster of a drawing made by Burnett. There is also a collection of more personal photos that include snapshots of Burnett with Gerald Ford, Betty Friedan, Gloria Steinem, and Indira Ghandi.
  - Personal Photos (Box 6)
  - The Portrait Club of New York, 1979-1998 (Box 8)
  - American Artist (Box 8)
  - Council of Leading Portrait Painters (Sanden) (Box 8)
  - Art Commissions -- Margaret Thatcher (Box 8)
  - Maura Corrigan (Box 8)
  - Flowers (Box 8)
  - N.O.W. (Box 8)
  - Scarab Club (Box 8)
  - Sketch Copies, photographs (Box 8)
  - Wilson, Ellen (Box 8)
  - Art -- General (Box 10)
  - Reference photos (Box 11)
    - Aquino -- Corozon (Box 11)
    - Barbara Walters (Box 11)
    - Betty Friedman (Box 11)
    - Cisler, Walker (Box 11)
    - Farenthold, Sissy (Box 11)
    - Fran Street (Box 11)
    - Fisher, Max (Box 11)
    - Ford, Benson (Box 11)
    - Ford, Betty, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Ford, Mrs. Edsel (Box 11)
    - Gribbs, Roman + Katherine (Box 11)
    - Governor John & Michele Engler (Box 11)
    - Governor Milliken (Box 11)
    - Honorable Helen Wilson Nies (Box 11)
    - Indira Ghandi (Box 11)
    - Kevorkian, Jack & Fieger, Geoffrey (Box 11)
    - Jackie Goiner Kersey (Box 11)
    - Judge Robert Young (Box 11)
    - Judge Ruth Bader Ginsberg (Box 11)
    - Mankiller, Wilma (Box 11)
    - Margaret Chase Smith, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Mayor Dennis Archer (Box 11)
    - Mayor Young (Box 11)
    - Oates, Joyce Carol (Box 11)
    - Ogden (Box 11)
    - Papandreou, Margaret (Box 11)
    - Parks, Rosa (Box 11)
    - Patricia Ireland (Box 11)
    - President Violeta de Chamorro (Box 11)
    - Shaw, Alden (Box 11)
    - Steinem, Gloria (Box 11)
    - Taylor, Clifford, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Tereshkova, Valentina, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Thatcher, Margaret (Box 11)
    - Thomas, Marlo (Box 11)
    - Vivica Lindfors (Box 11)
  - Lithographs and Watercolors (Box 12)
  - Collection of Portrait Copy Prints (Box 12)
  - Transparencies (Box 12)
  - Original drawing of Patricia Burnett (Folder 1)
  - Poster (drawing by Patricia Burnett) (Folder 1)
  - Original signed print by cartoonist Cathy Gwisewitz, also signed by Virginia Allen and Lynda Robb (Folder 1)